Chapter 26.
Sophie came at seven to dress me.
She was very long indeed in accomplishing her task, so long that Mr. Rochester,
grown, I suppose, impatient of my delay, sent up to ask why I did not come.
She was just fastening my veil, the plain square of blonde, after all,
to my hair with a brooch.
I hurried from under her hands as soon as I could.
Stop, she cried in French.
Look at yourself in the mirror, you have not taken one peep.
So I turned at the door.
I saw a robed and veiled figure, so unlike my usual
self that it seemed almost the image of a stranger.
Jane called a voice, and I hastened down.
I was received at the foot of the stairs by Mr. Rochester.
Lingerah, he said.
My brain is on fire with impatience and you tarry so long.
He took me into the dining-room, surveyed me keenly all over, pronounced me
fair as a lily, and not only the pride of his life, but the desire of his eyes,
and then telling me he would give me but ten minutes to eat some breakfast,
he rang the bell.
One of his lately-hired servants, a footman answered it.
Is John getting the carriage ready?
Yes, sir.
Is the luggage brought down?
They are bringing it down, sir.
Go you to the church.
See if Mr. Wood, the clergyman and the clerk are there.
Return and tell me.
The church, as the reader knows, was but just beyond the gates.
The footman soon returned.
Mr. Wood is in the vestry, sir, putting on his surplus.
And the carriage?
The horses are harnessing.
We shall not want it to go to church, but it must be ready the moment we return.
All the boxes and luggage arranged and strapped on in the coachman in his seat.
Yes, sir.
Jane, are you ready?
I rose.
There were no groomsmen, no bridesmaids, no relatives to wait for or marshal.
None but Mr. Rochester and I.
Mrs. Fairfax stood in the hall as we passed.
I would feign have spoken to her, but my hand was held by a grasp of iron.
I was hurried along by a stride I could hardly follow.
And to look at Mr. Rochester's face was to feel that not
a second of delay would be tolerated for any purpose.
I wonder what other bridegroom ever looked as he did, so bent up to a purpose,
so grimly resolute, or who, under such steadfast
brows, ever revealed such flaming and flashing eyes.
I know not whether the day was fair or foul.
In descending the drive I gazed neither on sky nor earth.
My heart was with my eyes, and both seemed migrated into Mr. Rochester's frame.
I wanted to see the invisible thing on which, as we went
along, he appeared to fasten a glance fierce and fell.
I wanted to feel the thoughts whose force he seemed resting and resisting.
At the churchyard wicked, he stopped.
He discovered I was quite out of breath.
Am I cruel in my love, he said.
Delay an instant, lean on me, Jane.
And now I can recall the picture of the gray old house of God rising calm before
me of a rook wheeling round the steeple of a ruddy morning sky beyond.
I remember something too of the green grave mounds, and I have not forgotten either.
Two figures of strangers straining amongst the low hillocks
and reading the mementos graven on the few mossy headstones.
I noticed them, because as they saw us, they passed round to the back of the
church, and I doubted not they were going to enter
by the side-ile door and witness the ceremony.
By Mr. Rochester, they were not observed.
He was earnestly looking at my face, from which the blood had, I daresay,
momentarily fled.
For I felt my forehead duly and my cheeks and lips cold.
When I rallied, which I soon did, he walked gently with me up the path to the porch.
We entered the quiet and humble temple.
The priest waited in his white surplus at the lowly altar, the clerk beside him.
All was still.
Two shadows only moved in a remote corner.
My conjecture had been correct.
The strangers had slipped in before us, and they now stood by the vault of the
Rochester's, their backs towards us, viewing through the rails the old time
-stained marble tomb, where a kneeling angel guarded the remains of Damodar
Rochester, slain at mastermore in the time of the civil wars and of Elizabeth,
his wife.
Our place was taken at the communion rails.
Hearing a cautious step behind me, I glanced over my shoulder.
One of the strangers, a gentleman evidently, was advancing up the chancel.
The service began.
The explanation of the intent of matrimony was gone through, and then the clergyman
came a step further forward, and bending slightly towards Mr.
Rochester, went on.
I require and charge you both, as you will answer at the dreadful day of
judgment, when the secrets of all hearts shall be disclosed.
That if either of you know any impediment, why you may not lawfully be joined
together in matrimony, you do now confess it.
For be you well assured that so many as are coupled together, otherwise than God's
word doth allow, are not joined together by God, neither is their matrimony lawful.
He paused, as the custom is.
When is the pause after that sentence ever broken
by reply, not perhaps once in a hundred years.
And the clergyman, who had not lifted his eyes from his book,
and had held his breath but for a moment, was proceeding.
His hand was already stretched towards Mr. Rochester, as his lips unclosed to ask,
will thou have this woman for thy wedded wife, when a distinct and near voice said,
the marriage cannot go on.
I declare the existence of an impediment.
The clergyman looked up at the speaker and stood mute.
The clerk did the same.
Mr. Rochester moved slightly, as if an earthquake had rolled under his feet,
taking a firmer footing, and not turning his head or eyes, he said, proceed,
profound silence fell when he had uttered that word, with deep but low intonation.
Presently Mr. Wood said, I cannot proceed without some investigation into what has
been asserted and evidence of its truth or falsehood.
The ceremony is quite broken off, subjoined the voice behind us.
I am in a condition to prove my allegation, an
insuperable impediment to this marriage exists.
Mr. Rochester heard, but he did not.
He stood stubborn and rigid, making no movement but to possess himself of my hand.
What a hot and strong grass he had, and how like quarried marble was his pale,
firm, massive front at this moment.
How his eyes shone, still watchful, and yet wild beneath Mr. Wood seemed at a loss.
What is the nature of the impediment, he asked?
Perhaps it may be got over, explained away?
Hardly was the answer.
I have called it insuperable and I speak advisedly.
The speaker came forward and leaned on the rails.
He continued, uttering each word distinctly, calmly, steadily, but not loudly.
It simply consists in the existence of a previous marriage.
Mr. Rochester has a wife now living.
My nerves vibrated to those low spoken words, as they had never vibrated to thunder.
My blood felt their subtle violence, as it had never felt frost or fire.
But I was collected, and in no danger of swooning.
I looked at Mr. Rochester.
I made him look at me.
His whole face was colourless rock.
His eye was both spark and flint.
He disavowed nothing.
He seemed as if he would defy all things, without speaking, without smiling,
without seeming to recognise in me a human being.
He only twined my waist with his arm and riveted me to his side.
Who are you?
He asked of the intruder.
My name is Briggs, a solicitor of Aar Street, London.
And you would thrust on me a wife?
I would remind you of your lady's existence,
sir, which the law recognises if you do not.
Fave a me with an account of her, with her name,
her parentage, her place of abode, certainly.
Mr. Briggs calmly took a paper from his pocket
and read out in a sort of official nasal voice.
I affirm and can prove that on the 20th of October AD, a date of 15 years back,
Edward Fairfax Rochester, of Thornfield Hall, in the county of Conca, and of
Fendin Manor, in Na'an Shire, England, was married to my sister, Bertha
Antoinette Mason, daughter of Jonas Mason, Merchant, and of Antoinette, his wife,
a Creole, at my church, Spanish town Jamaica.
The record of the marriage will be found in the register of that church.
A copy of it is now in my possession, signed Richard Mason.
That, if a genuine document, may prove I have been married, but it does not prove
that the woman mentioned therein as my wife is still living.
She was living three months ago, returned the lawyer.
How do you know?
I have a witness to the fact, whose testimony,
even you, sir, will scarcely contribute.
Produce him or go to hell.
I will produce him first.
He is on the spot.
Mr. Mason have the goodness to step forward.
Mr. Rochester, on hearing the name, set his teeth.
He experienced two a sort of strong, convulsive quiver.
Near to him, as I was, I felt the spasmodic
movement of fury or despair run through his frame.
The second stranger, who had hitherto lingered in the background, now drew near.
A pale face looked over the solicitor's shoulder.
Yes, it was Mason himself.
Mr. Rochester turned and glared at him.
His eye, as I have often said, was a black eye.
It had now a tawny nay, a bloody light in its gloom, and his face flushed.
Olive cheek and heueless forehead received a glow as from spreading ascending
heartfire, and he stirred, lifted his strong arm.
He could have struck Mason, dashed him on the church
floor, shocked by ruthless blow the breath from his body.
But Mason shrank away and cried faintly, Good God!
Contempt fell cool on Mr. Rochester.
His passion died as if a blight had shriveled it up.
He only asked, What have you to say?
An inaudible reply escaped Mason's white lips.
The devil is in it if you cannot answer distinctly.
I again demand, What have you to say?
Sir, Sir, Interrupted the clergyman.
Do not forget you are in a sacred place.
Then addressing Mason, he inquired gently.
Are you aware, Sir, whether or not this gentleman's wife is still living?
Courage urged the lawyer, Speak out.
She is now living at Thornfield Hall, said Mason, in more articulate tones.
I saw her there last April.
I am her brother.
At Thornfield Hall, ejaculated the clergyman.
Impossible.
I am an old resident in this neighborhood, Sir, and I never heard of a Mrs.
Rochester at Thornfield Hall.
I saw a grim smile, contort Mr. Rochester's lips.
And he muttered, No, by God.
I took care that none should hear of it, or of her under that name.
He mused.
For ten minutes he held counsel with himself.
He formed his resolve and announced it.
Enough.
All shall bolt out at once, like the bullet from the barrel.
Wood, close your book and take off your surplus.
John Green, to the clerk.
Leave the church.
There will be no wedding today.
The man obeyed.
Mr. Rochester continued, hardly and recklessly.
Bigamy is an ugly word.
I meant, however, to be a bigamist, but fate has outmaneuvered me,
or providence has checked me.
Perhaps the last.
I am little better than a devil at this moment.
And, as my pastor there would tell me, deserve no doubt the sternest judgments of
God, even to the quenchless fire and deathless worm.
Gentlemen, my plan is broken up.
What this lawyer and his clients say is true.
I have been married, and the woman to whom I was married lives.
You say you never heard of a Mrs. Rochester at the house up Yonderwood,
but I dare say you have many a time inclined your ear to gossip about the
mysterious lunatic, kept there under watch and ward.
Some have whispered to you that she is my bastard half sister.
Some, my cast off mistress.
I now inform you that she is my wife, whom I married 15 years ago.
Bertha Mason, by name, sister of this resolute personage, who is now,
with his quivering limbs and white cheeks,
showing you what a stout heart men may bear.
Cheer up, Dick, never fear me.
I'd almost as soon strike a woman as you.
Bertha Mason is mad, and she came of a mad family,
idiots and maniacs through three generations.
Her mother, the Creole, was both a mad woman and a
drunkard, as I found out after I had wed the daughter.
For they were silent on family secrets before.
Bertha, like a beautiful child, copied her parent in both points.
I had a charming partner, pure, wise, modest.
You can fancy?
I was a happy man.
I went through rich scenes.
Oh, my experience has been heavenly if you only knew it.
But I owe you no further explanation.
Briggs, would, Mason, I invite you all to come up to the house and visit Mrs.
Paul's patient and my wife.
You shall see what sort of a being I was cheated into espousing.
And judge whether or not I had a right to break the
compact and seek sympathy with something at least human.
This girl, he continued, looking at me, knew no
more than you would of the disgusting secret.
She thought all was fair and legal, and never dreamt she was going to be
entrapped into a fained union with a defrauded wretch, already bound to a bad,
mad, and imbruted partner.
Come, all of you, follow.
Still holding me fast, he left the church.
The three gentlemen came after.
At the front door of the hall, we found the carriage.
Take it back to the coach house, John, said Mr. Rochester Cooley.
It will not be wanted today.
At our entrance, Mrs. Fairfax, Adele, Sophie, Leah, advanced to meet and greet us.
To the right about every soul, cried the master, away with your
congratulations, who wants them, not I, they are 15 years too late.
He passed on and ascended the stairs, still holding my hand, and still beckoning
the gentleman to follow him, which they did.
We mounted the first staircase, passed up the gallery, preceded to the third story.
The low black door, opened by Mr. Rochester's master key, admitted us to the
tapestry room, with its great bed and its pictorial cabinet.
You know this place, Mason, said our guide.
She bit and stabbed you here.
He lifted the hangings from the wall, uncovering the second door.
This, too, he opened.
In a room without a window, their burnt a fire guarded by a high and strong fender,
and a lamp suspended from the ceiling by a chain.
Grace pool bent over the fire, apparently cooking something in a saucepan.
In the deep shade, at the farther end of the
room, a figure ran backwards and forwards.
What it was, where the beast or human being, one could not, at first sight, tell.
It groveled, seemingly on all fours.
It snatched and growled like some strange wild animal, but it was covered with
clothing, and a quantity of dark, grizzled hair, wild as a main,
hid its head and face.
Good morning, Mrs. Pool, said Mr. Rochester.
How are you, and how's your charge today?
We're tolerable, sir.
I thank you," replied Grace, lifting the boiling mess carefully onto the hob,
rather snappish, but not rages.
A fierce cry seemed to give the lie to her favorable report.
The clothed hyena rose up and stood tall on its hind feet.
Ah, sir, she sees you.
Exclaimed Grace.
You'd better not stay.
Only a few moments Grace, you must allow me a few moments.
Take care then, sir.
For God's sake, take care.
The maniac bellowed.
She parted her shaggy locks from her visage and gazed wildly at her visitors.
I recognized well that purple face.
Those bloated features.
Mrs. Pool advanced.
Keep out of the way, said Mr. Rochester, thrusting her aside.
She has no knife now, I suppose, and I'm on my guard.
One never knows what she has, sir.
She is so cunning, it is not in mortal discretion to fathom her craft.
We had better leave her, whispered Mason.
Go to the devil.
Was his brother-in-law's recommendation.
Where, cried Grace?
The three gentlemen retreated simultaneously.
Mr. Rochester flung me behind him.
The lunatic sprang and grappled his throat viciously and laid her teeth to his cheek.
They struggled.
She was a big woman.
In stature almost equalling her husband and corpulant
besides, she showed virile force in the contest.
More than once she almost throttled him, athletic as he was.
He could have settled her with a well -planted blow, but he would not strike.
He would only wrestle.
At last, he mastered her arms.
Grace Pool gave him a cord and he pinioned them behind her.
With more rope, which was at hand, he bound her to a chair.
The operation was performed amidst the fiercest yells in the most convulsive plunges.
Mr. Rochester then turned to the spectators.
He looked at them with a smile both accurate and desolate.
That is my wife, said he.
Such is the soul conjugal embrace I am ever to know.
Such are the demons which are to solace my leisure hours.
And this is what I wished to have.
Laying his hand on my shoulder, this young girl, who stands so grave and
quiet at the mouth of hell, looking collectively at the gambles of a demon,
I wanted her just as a change after that fierce ragu.
Wooden Briggs, look at the difference.
Compare these clear eyes with the red balls yonder, this face with that mask,
this form with that bulk.
Then judge me, priest of the gospel and man of the law, and remember with what
judgment ye judge ye shall be judged, off with you now.
I must shut up my prize.
We all withdrew.
Mr. Rochester stayed a moment behind us to give some further order to grace pool.
The solicitor addressed me as he descended the stair.
You, madam, said he, are cleared from all blame.
Your uncle will be glad to hear it if, indeed, he should be still living when Mr.
Mason returns to Madera.
My uncle, what of him?
Do you know him?
Mr. Mason does.
Mr. Ayer has been the funshell correspondent of his house for some years.
When your uncle received your letter intimating, the contemplated union between
yourself and Mr. Rochester, Mr. Mason, who was staying at Madera to recruit his
health on his way back to Jamaica, happened to be with him.
Mr. Ayer mentioned the intelligence, for he knew that my client here was
acquainted with a gentleman of the name of Rochester.
Mr. Mason, astonished and distressed as you may
suppose, revealed the real state of matters.
Your uncle, I am sorry to say, is now on a sick bed, from which,
considering the nature of his disease, decline and the stage it has reached,
it is unlikely he will ever rise.
He could not then hasten to England himself, to extricate you from the snare
into which you had fallen, but he implored Mr. Mason to
lose no time in taking steps to prevent the false marriage.
He referred him to me for assistance.
I used all dispatch, and I am thankful I was not too late, as you, doubtless,
must be also.
Were I not morally certain that your uncle will be dead air you reach Madera,
I would advise you to accompany Mr. Mason back, but as it is, I think you'd better
remain in England till you can else to stay for.
He inquired of Mr. Mason.
No, no, let us be gone, was the anxious reply.
And without waiting to take leave of Mr. Rochester,
they made their exit at the hall door.
The clergyman stayed to exchange a few sentences, either
of admonition or reproof with his haughty parishioner.
This duty done, he too departed.
I heard him go, as I stood at the half -open door
of my own room, to which I had now withdrawn.
The house cleared, I shut myself in, fastened the bolt that none might intrude
and proceeded, not to weep, not to mourn, I was yet too calm for that, mechanically
to take off the wedding dress and replace it by the stuff gown I had worn yesterday,
as I thought for the last time.
I then sat down.
I felt weak and tired.
I leaned my arms on a table and my head dropped on them, and now I thought,
till now I had only heard scene moved, followed up and down where I was led or
dragged, watched event, rush on event, disclosure opened beyond disclosure,
but now I thought.
The morning had been a quiet morning enough,
all except the brief scene with the lunatic.
The transaction in the church had not been noisy.
There was no explosion of passion, no loud altercation, no dispute,
no defiance or challenge, no tears, no sobs.
A few words had been spoken, a calmly pronounced objection to the marriage made,
some stern, short questions put by Mr. Rochester, answers, explanations given,
evidence-adduced, an open admission of the truth had been uttered by my master.
Then the living proof had been seen, the intruders were gone, and all was over.
I was in my own room as usual, just myself, without obvious change.
Nothing had smitten me, or scathed me, or maimed
me, and yet, where was the Jane Eyre of yesterday?
Where was her life?
Where were her prospects?
Jane Eyre, who had been an ardent, expectant woman almost a bride,
was a cold solitary girl again.
Her life was pale, her prospects were desolate.
A Christmas frost had come at mid-summer, a white December storm had whirled over June.
Ice glazed the ripe apples, drifts crushed the blowing roses, on hayfield and
cornfield lay a frozen shroud, lanes which last night blushed full of flowers.
Today were pathless with untrodden snow, and the woods, which 12 hours since waved
leafy and fragrant as groves between the tropics, now spread, waste, wild,
and white as pine forests in wintry Norway.
My hopes were all dead, struck with a subtle doom, such as
in one night fell on all the firstborn in the land of Egypt.
I looked on my cherished wishes, yesterday so blooming and glowing,
they lay stark, chill, livid corpses that could never revive.
I looked at my love, that feeling which was my masters, which he had created.
It shivered in my heart, like a suffering child in a cold cradle.
Sickness and anguish had seized it.
It could not seek Mr. Rochester's arms.
It could not derive warmth from his breast.
Oh, never more could it turn to him.
For faith was blighted.
Confidence destroyed.
Mr. Rochester was not to me what he had been, for he was not what I had thought him.
I would not ascribe vice to him.
I would not say he had betrayed me, but the attribute of stainless truth was
gone from his idea, and from his presence I must go, that I perceived well.
When, how, wither, I could not yet discern, but he himself I doubted not,
would hurry me from thornfield.
Real affection it seemed he could not have for me.
It had been only fitful passion.
That was balked.
He would want me no more.
I should fear even to cross his path now.
My view must be hateful to him.
Oh, how blind had been my eyes, how weak my conduct.
My eyes were covered and closed.
Eddying darkness seemed to swim around me, and
reflection came in as black and confused a flow.
Self-abandoned, relaxed and effortless.
I seemed to have laid me down in the dried up bed of a great river.
I heard a flood loosened in remote mountains, and felt the torrent come.
To rise I had no will.
To flee I had no strength.
I lay faint, longing to be dead.
One idea only still throbbed life like within me.
A remembrance of God.
It begot an unuttered prayer.
These words went wandering up and down in my railous mind, a something that should
be whispered, but no energy was found to express them.
Be not far from me.
For trouble is near.
There is none to help.
It was near, and as I had lifted no petition to heaven to avert it,
as I had neither joined my hands nor bent my knees nor moved my lips.
It came.
In full heavy swing the torrent poured over me, the whole consciousness of my
life -lawn, my love-lost, my hope -quenched, my faith-death-struck,
swayed full and mighty above me in one's sullen mass.
That bitter hour cannot be described.
In truth, the waters came into my soul.
I sank in deep mire.
I felt no standing.
I came into deep waters.
The floods overflowed me.
Chapter 27 Sometime in the afternoon I raised my head, and looking round and
seeing the western sun gilding the sign of its decline on the wall, I asked,
what am I to do?
But the answer my mind gave, leave Thornfield at once, was so prompt,
so dread, that I stopped my ears.
I said I could not bear such words now.
That I am not Edward Rochester's bride is the least part of my woe, I alleged,
that I have wakened out of most glorious dreams, and found
them all void and vain is a horror I could bear and master.
But that I must leave him decidedly, instantly, entirely, is intolerable.
I cannot do it.
But then, a voice within me, a bird that I
could do it, and foretold that I should do it.
I wrestled with my own resolution.